<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The best way of using the true salt polychrest of Messieurs Seignette of Rochel</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2059aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232527</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898009</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898009</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76467)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2546:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The best way of using the true salt polychrest of Messieurs Seignette of Rochel</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXV. [1685]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an advertisement at the foot of p. 30.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Potassium in the body --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Potassium salts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Beſt Way OF Uſing the True Salt POLYCHREST OF <hi>MESSIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RS SEIGNETTE</hi> OF ROCHEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author. MDCLXXXV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171007:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171007:2"/>
            <head>The beſt Way of Uſing the true Salt <hi>Polychrest</hi> of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieurs Seignette</hi> of Rochel.</head>
            <p>THis Remedy has got ſuch a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation abroad, that 'tis no Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if ſome People have been and are ſtill very eager to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it. So natural it is for Mankind to inquire into all Things; and ſuch is the Duty incumbent on thoſe who take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the Cure of Diſeaſes, as to omit nothing that may conduce to ſo great a Thing as Health is. But we have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to wonder both at the Ignorance and Baſeneſs of thoſe Men, who, abuſing the Truſt we had repoſed in them for the Sale of this Polychreſt, have coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited it, and do ſtill counterfeit it (as doth one <hi>Mr. Rouſſean</hi> in Paris)
<pb facs="tcp:171007:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171007:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171007:4"/>with a Mixture of Sulphur and Saltpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter burnt together. The Effects of which have been too fatal, and have ſufficiently taught us how dangerous it was to be ſurpriſed by the Equivoque of a Name ſignifying ſo contrary Things. It was upon that ground that in the Year 1675 we publiſhed a Treatiſe of all the Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our <hi>Polychrest</hi> that were then made, wherein we made it appear how much they differed from ours. Of which Truth the Learned were ſo fully convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, upon a ſtrict Inquiry made in that Juncture of Time in the moſt famous Univerſities of <hi>France,</hi> and by the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments that were made of it in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, that I need not inlarge upon it.</p>
            <p>The only Deſign of theſe Papers is, to ſhew how to uſe this Remedy more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodically and to more Advantage than has been done hitherto; and to declare withall, that we have took away the Selling of it from <hi>Mr. Angibaud,</hi> a French Apothecary living in S. Martins Lane, who was intruſted with the Sale thereof. For, having made an ill Uſe of the Truſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171007:4"/>we had put in him, and taking an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of our dwelling out of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, he has made bold to put off, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our Name and Seal, a Powder of his own making. Which has proved ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, and has ſo far indangered the Lives of ſome Perſons of great Quality in this Kingdom, that the true Polychreſt was brought into Suſpicion. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was natural enough for Perſons that could not, through ſuch a cunning Diſguiſe, and ſo deceitful an Outſide, diſcen the true Remedy from the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, to exclaim againſt the true one, and charge it as a miſchievous Thing, though never ſo beneficial to Mankind.</p>
            <p>This very Thing was fit to be took notice of, the rather for that our Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and the Lives of ſuch Perſons are at ſtake, and becauſe <hi>Mr. Angibaud</hi> (as we are informed) continues to ſell his Polychreſt, contrary to a Promiſe he hath given us under his own hand, that he would not meddle with it any more. 'Tis true he has dreſſed it up with new Covers, and that the Name and Town
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171007:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>printed thereon are ſufficient Marks to diſtinguiſh it from ours. But, if on the one ſide he has ſtripped it of its former borrowed Out-ſide, he has inriched it on the other with the Spoils of a ſmall Treatiſe publiſhed by us in French about fifteen Years ſince. Inſomuch that he gives his Polychreſt all the Virtues of ours, though he knows well enough, and has been told of it ſufficiently, that there is a vaſt Difference.</p>
            <p>This ſecond Shift is no leſs captious and cunning than the firſt. For he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw very well, that few Perſons would give themſelves the trouble of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Copy with the Original. And, if any were ſo far curious, he knew they could but commend him for his faithful Tranſlation, for having followed his Text cloſe, without adding or diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without changing the Words or the Senſe, but rendering the Whole, word for word, out of French into Engliſh. The Gentleman was ſenſible, that in ſuch a Caſe as this, if any, he muſt be ſtrict and conſcientious, and do things
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:171007:5"/>
               <hi>bonâ fide.</hi> The Truth is, we cannot but commend his for it, and return him Thanks forſooth for the Reſpect he ſhewed to our Treatiſe, ſo far as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it ſhould contain all the Virtues of his Powder, and that it was of it ſelf ſufficient to cry it up. One good Turn deſerves another; and 'tis but fit we ſhould expreſs our Gratitude to him by theſe two good Offices.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I ſhall make his Apology againſt thoſe that might find fault with him for having altered the Method of our Book which he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to tranſcribe. For, whereas we had ſpoke but towards the end of it of the Uſe which might be made of our <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chreſt</hi> with Mineral Waters, without opening at large the Advantages that might come by it, he began his Treatiſe by ſhewing how eaſily his Powder is diſſolved in the ſaid Waters, and how it brings them out of the Body, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by Stools, and ſometimes by Urine. Now this Tranſpoſition is certainly very judicious, and nothing could be better
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:171007:6"/>contrived for his purpoſe, being it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all the Virtues one may moſt ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally attribute unto his Powder. Which, if capable of producing any good Effect, muſt needs do it on this Occaſion. 'Tis well known, that moſt of the Salts uſed in Phyſick, being ſuſpected in a ſmall quantity of Water, may be drunk with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Fear, being well diſſolved, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in that vaſt Quantity of Water which ſome People uſe to drink up.</p>
            <p>In the next place we ſhall do him the Kindneſs to ſhew him a more ready, and perhaps a cheaper, Way than he has to make his Powder. Let him but take what Quantity he pleaſes of Salt of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or of any other Alkali, fixed and well-purified, and add to it a reaſonable quantity of acid Spirit, and he ſhall ſee preſently all his Salt purified and chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtallized. If he queſtion this Experiment, he may inquire about it of the Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and other Virtuoſi, in whoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence I made it. They will aſſure him, that out of that Mixture of Acid and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kali, there comes a Salt of the ſame Taſte
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:171007:6"/>and nature as his, that will ſtand any Proof. They will teſtify unto him, that, after it is dryed up and pulverized, if it be thrown into cold Water, it is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly congealed, and turned into chryſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line lumps, inſtead of being diſſolved; that thoſe Chryſtals are long, ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and eaſily reduced into Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, their figure coming near thoſe of Saltpeter; that being put upon glowing Coals, they melt away to Water, and that in the quenching of them they make them cake together by a kind of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. They will further tell him, that the ſame Chryſtals being expoſed to a moderate Heat, or to an Air ſomewhat dry, loſe preſently their from, and are reduced into a Powder almoſt impalpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. By thoſe Gentlemen he ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that our Salt is (much like Caſhoo) bitter-ſweet, that it eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves in the Water, that its Chryſtals are hard, compacted, and of the figure of Lozenges, that they never diſſolve in the Air nor yet in the Fire, that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quench burning Coals nor make
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:171007:7"/>them Cake; but on the contrary grow red-hot like Iron, and loſe only their Tranſparence, without receiving any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Alteration whatſoever.</p>
            <p>The averſion that People always had againſt Phyſical Remedy's, but chiefly againſt Purges, has given us occaſion to go about to correct the ſame, and to take off from them that unpleaſant Taſt and dreadful Colour which daunts the ſpirits of the ſtouteſt Men, and often deprives them from the benefit which might be got by thoſe Remedy's. To compaſs our Deſign, that which ſeemed moſt proper for it is the Matter of Salts; which is not only of the greateſt lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but withall includes in it ſelf all the Virtue inherent in the Mixts, and contains in a ſhort compaſs what is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed in other Body's. Therefore we made choice of three ſorts of Salt, the beſt known to us, to compoſe a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of many Uſes in Phyſick, and ſuch as could be taken without any great caution. Which Remdey we named
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:171007:7"/>
               <hi>Polychreſt,</hi> from a Greek Word that ſignify's a Thing of ſeveral Uſes.</p>
            <p>And indeed in the firſt place it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, without irritation and pain, the groſs Excrements and the moſt viſcous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, ſo that it may be ſafely admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the weakeſt Perſons, and to Women at any time of their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, even when they have upon them thoſe griping Pains which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the fore-runners of a Labour. And, as it is ſafe and proper to Women in that Condition before their Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, ſo it is in their After-pains whilſt they ly in Child-bed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this <hi>Polychreſt</hi> is excellent to remove Obſtructions in any part of the Body whatever, and likewiſe to correct the putrify'd Maſs of the Blood, and reſtore it to its natural ſtate. Which two Property's are of that great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that they ſhould make the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt ſo much the more valuable; but they are Things the leaſt known, and therefore the leaſt regarded. For many People are prepoſſeſſed, that a Phyſick
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:171007:8"/>don't work, and no Good is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from it, unleſs it works violently, and carry's off wth it a great deal of thick Matter; as if this were the only Way to eaſe Nature, and the Cure of all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes ſhould depend upon thoſe Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuations.</p>
            <p>Theſe Things being premiſed, our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is now to propoſe a ſhort and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Method, that may ſerve on the one ſide as a Guide and Direction for the ſick, and a Ground-plot on the other ſide for ſuch as ſhall be appointed to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter this phyſical Remedy. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that it will be an eaſy matter for theſe, according to their Inſight and Experience in Phyſick, to ſtretch or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it, as Occaſion ſhall ſerve, having ſtill a regard to the differency of Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and the ſymptoms that may happen. I have frobore to deſcend to Particulars, and that for theſe three Reaſons. Firſt, becauſe they may be eaſily diſcovered. Secondly, becauſe otherwiſe they may be left to the care and fidelity of the Patients Phyſician. And thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:171007:8"/>
               <hi>Mr. Angibaud</hi> has ſaved us the trouble of it by publiſhing our fore-men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Treatiſe, which I ſuppoſe has been read by ſeveral.</p>
            <p>Therefore it will be ſufficient to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve three principal Ways, in the Uſe of our Polychreſt, according to the three Intentions one ought to have in the Cure of Diſeaſes. The firſt is in order to Purge the groſs Excrements, and all the filth that remains in the Ventricle. The ſecond is, to allay and diſſolve the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors that ly ſtagnant in the inward Parts, as the Liver, Spleen, Reins, Meſenterium, Pancreas, and the Womb. The third is, to make it circulate with the Blood, to correct and purify it when putrid, to ſweeten it when it is come to be too ſharp or acid, to make it fluid when too thick to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it ſelf through all the Parts of the Body, or when it is ſo active and violent as to run without giving any nouriſhment of Spirits want ſtill to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing waſted of Spirits want ſtill to be recruited. Now theſe are the Ways
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:171007:9"/>called by the Phyſicians, <hi>Prima, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunda, &amp; Tertia Via,</hi> this laſt being the remoteſt of all.</p>
            <p>The common Doſe of this Remedy to Purge the firſt Way is ſix Drams, to be put in a Quart or three parts of a Quart of Water, or of any other Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quour. But one may take a leſſer quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity both of the Powder and Liquour, according to the Age and Strength of the Patient. As for a Child one or two years of age, the fourth part of the Doze will be enough, being taken in four or five ounces of blood-warm Milk, and that in the ſpace of five or ſix hours, one hour before and after it has ſucked. Half the Doze in a Pint of Water will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for a Child five or ſix years old; which he may take at any time of the Day, provided it be ſome time before he eats, or after he has eaten. The two thirds of the Doze in three parts of a Quart of Water is proper for a Child ten or eleven years old. And laſtly, the whole Doze in a Quart or three parts of a Quart of Water, for any Perſon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:171007:9"/>fifteen years of Age, and all above that Age. As for ſuch Perſons who, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the weakneſs of their Stomach, cannot bear with ſuch a quantity of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they may freely reduce it to a Pint, ſteeping ſome Licoriſh therein, to take off a bitteriſh kind of Taſte which ſome Perſons might be diſguſted at.</p>
            <p>The moſt proper Time to purge with this Remedy is in the Morning, faſting. But, in caſe of Neceſſity, it may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at any time of the Day, except im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Meals. Two or three Hours after one has drunk the laſt Glaſs of the Doze, he may take ſome Veal or Mutton-broth.</p>
            <p>In general 'tis to be obſerved, that in all Diſeaſes contracted by an abundance of Humours, but eſpecially by viſcous and melancholy Humours, ſuch as hinder the Digeſtion and interrupt the courſe of the animal Spirits (which is obſervable in a ſick Body, by a low intermittent Pulſe) the whole Doze muſt be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts of a Quart at the moſt, or a Pint of Spring-water warmed, or elſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:171007:10"/>inſtead of common Water, in ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctions of Roots, Barks, and Aromatical Herbs, the better to extenuate and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide that groſs and viſcous Humour. And becauſe it ſometimes falls out in ſuch Diſeaſes, that the Patient brings up all the Doze, or ſome part of it, the Way to remedy that is to take again as much of the Doſe as is come up, thereby to open the Paſſage to and precipitate the Humours. But, if the Patient continue to vomit (which happens but too often) then we make uſe of a purging Salt; and this we give either alone, or with the fourth part of the Doze of Polychreſt, in two Glaſſes of warm Water, or elſe in ſome cooling Broth. Which Salt do's evacuate much more than the Polychreſt, and is moſt proper in this Exigence.</p>
            <p>But in ſuch Diſeaſes as proceed from the overflowing of the Choler, which rarifying or mingling it ſelf with the other Humours, cauſes Fermentations in the Blood, and provokes Keckings and Vomitings, it is more proper to put the Doze of Polychreſt into a Quart or three
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:171007:10"/>pints of Spring-water, and to drink it cold by degrees, one Glaſs full every Hour or Half-hour. But, if the Patient be under any great Pains, either of Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick or Diarrhaea, he may take the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in the ſame quantity of Water ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hot, and as is before ſaid.</p>
            <p>This Remedy does not only purge gently, but corrects alſo the Violence of all other Purges, if one put but one half or a fourth part of the Doze into their Infuſion. It has alſo a ſingular Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtop and appeaſe the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting occaſioned by the moſt powerful Emeticks; which do not only give ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Jerks to the Membranes of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, but leave commonly a bad Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, eſpecially upon a weak Stomach. To prevent which, put a third part, or one half of our Doze, into one half pint of cold Water, and take it half an Hour before the Emetick. And, if the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Emetick be ſuch as to cauſe too violent and conſtant a Vomiting, 'tis but taking the fourth part of the Doze into a great Glaſs of Water or warm De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:171007:11"/>The Vomit having done work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there remains ſtill commonly ſome Diſpoſition to vomit, with a ſwimming of the Head; and the long ſtay either of Antimony, or of any other Emetick in the Stomack, is known to be of a dangerous Conſequence. Which to avoid, do but take one half or a third part of the Doze of Polychreſt in a great Glaſs of Water. The ſame will remove the pricking of the Sulphurs and the Salts of Antimony, and precipitate them with the Humours diſgorged into the Stomack by the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Parts, which is the moſt natural Way.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Way is to remove the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which are bred in the Liver, Spleen, and Meſenterium, in the Pancre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, the Reins, the Bladder, and the Womb; from whence proceed a great number of long and ſtubborn Diſeaſes, ſuch as Rhumatiſms, heavineſs of the Head and Head-akes, Sleepineſs, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy, Palſy, Cachexy, Jaundice, the Dropſy either of the Brain or Breaſt, of the low Belly or the Womb, the Aſthma, or ſhortneſs of Breath, Iſchuries or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:171007:11"/>of Urine, the Nephreticks, the Gout, and Sciatick. To which add di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe other Diſeaſes, cauſed by thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; which do not only obſtruct the Paſſage of the Blood, but make it beſides too ſharp and too brackiſh. And of this Number I reckon Reſtleſneſs, great Pains in the Head, Giddineſs, Phrenſy, the Contractions of the Nerves, Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Inflammations of the Breaſt, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterical or Hypocondriacal Vapours, and the Scurvy.</p>
            <p>In all which Diſeaſes, the chief end of this Remedy being to ſeparate and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the thick and ſtagnant Humours that lay in the narroweſt Paſſages, and to give free paſſage to the Blood, and to the motion of the Spirits, this following Method is to be obſerved.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, the Patient is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by a Purge with a Doze of the Polychreſt, in a pint or a pint and a half of River or Spring Water, to carry off by this means the courſeſt Excrements, and to facilitate the diſtribution of the remedy through all the Parts of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:171007:12"/>Body. After which, the very Night af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Purge, he may put a Doze in a quart or three pints of Water, and take a great Glaſs of it three hours after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and another the next day very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he may ſleep upon it, and the reſt in the Day-time between Meals, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing the uſe of it during five or ſix Days more or leſs, according to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Diſeaſe, and the Condition of the Diſeaſed. Nay he may, if he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (which is our uſual Method) forbear drinking of it between Meals, ſo he takes a great Glaſs in the Night when he goes to Bed, and the reſt in the Morning faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the compaſs of two or three Hours.</p>
            <p>But for a greater eaſe to the Patient, and to follow the Indications that offer themſelves, it is proper enough to put the Remedy into different Liquours. So, when the Patient is of a bilious Temper, it may be put in Liquours made ſowriſh with the Juice of Lemons, Gooſeberry's, or Barberry's, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if he be of a moiſt or pituitous Temper, let it be put in Ptiſanes,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:171007:12"/>or Decoctions, made with Roots, Barks, Leaves, or aromatical Flowers. And, if one would have theſe Liquors work by Stools rather than Urine, they muſt be drunk very warm, walking abroad in the Air, or taking ſome other Exerciſe. But, if he had rather they ſhould work by Urine than by Stools, he muſt take it cold, and that by Intervals, keeping his Bed or his Chamber, and adding to his Doze a little Spirit of Sulphur or Vitriol. Inſtead of Decoctions he may uſe River-water, which runs through the Body much quicker than Spring-water. The ſame will become mineral, and very ſtrong, if one put the fourth or third part of the Doze upon two Quarts to be drunk in the Morning, faſting, within the compaſs of two or three Hours, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the firſt five or ſix Days, diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards the Doze of the Powder to the fourth part or ſomething leſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Quantity of Water. The uſe whereof muſt be continued yet a while, according to the Patient's Diſtemper.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:171007:13"/>
            <p>The Third and laſt Way of uſing this phyſical Remedy is in order to have it mingled with the Chylus and the Blood; that running by this means into the moſt ſecret Conduits, it may qualifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh the too ſharp and inflamed Choler, correct and dulcifie the other Juices too acid or too corroding, and reſtore the whole Maſs of Blood to its true Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, and that balſamick Quality it muſt have to diſtribute to all Parts of the Body the Nouriſhment they want. To do this effectually, the two firſt Ways muſt be made uſe of, or elſe one muſt be at leaſt ſufficiently purged. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, put the third part of the Doze into a Quart of Water, or any other convenient Liquor, and take a Glaſs on't two hours after Suppper, and another in the Morning. Sleep upon it, if you can poſſibly, and drink the reſt in the Day-time, an Hour before every Meal, and two or three Hours after. So the whole Doze will be taken in twenty four Hours, whereby the Patient ſhall be brought to a good Temper, and find a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:171007:13"/>great deal of eaſe; his Water will come more freely, and his Belly will be looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, without any other ſenſible Effect. If ſo be the Patient is of a lean and dry Conſtitution, or is waſted away by his long Diſtemper, 'tis fit in ſuch a Caſe he ſhould be bathed in a Room for ſeveral days together, or (if he be too weak) every other day. But the Water muſt only be lukewarm, whereby to provoke an inſenſible Tranſpiration, or at the moſt a little Moiſture on the Skin. And, during the Bath, the Polychreſt ſhall be uſed juſt as before, only the Patient ſhall drink a Glaſs on't at his entring into the Bath, and ſome Glaſſes while he is in. Which Method is to be obſerved in all Diſeaſes proceeding from the Corruption of the Blood; ſuch as conſumptive, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid, and hectick Fevers, quotidian, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, and double tertian Agues; alſo in all Venereal Diſeaſes, and all ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from an exceeding great Efferveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency or Irritation of Humours, as bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Fluxes, whether they proceed from the Brain, or from the Breaſt, from the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:171007:14"/>Stomach, or the Reins, from the Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhoids, or the Womb. But, if the Patient be fat, and of a moiſt Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion, 'tis fit he ſhould take ſome Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe during this Uſe of the Remedy, and a convenient Sweating will be very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for him.</p>
            <p>Thus you have in general the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of this Remedy, and the Method to be uſed for the Cure of the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Diſeaſes. Thoſe that judge only of the Goodneſs of Phyſick by the great quantity of Drugs, and that are uſed to ſeek their Eaſe in great Compoſitions (though their Virtue does commonly fall ſhort of their ſhew) will undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look upon the Virtues we attribute to our Salt, as a Piece of Exaggeration. But we are fully perſwaded on the other ſide, that thoſe who underſtand Phyſick, being conſcious that the plaineſt Phyſicks are the beſt, will think well of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; eſpecially if they do but examine the Nature of it, and conſider the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Salts and mineral Waters, the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof do oftentimes exceed the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:171007:14"/>Expectation both of thoſe that take them, and of thoſe that preſcribe 'em.</p>
            <p>What remains, before we conclude, is to acquaint you, that our Reflections and long Experience have taught us, that Polychreſt does not work upon all Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions alike, but that it operates beſt in caſe of a Cholick, a Diarrhea, and Gripings in the Guts, in an over-flowing of the Choler, in hyſterical Suffocations and melancholy Vapours, and in the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrual Retentions. Upon theſe Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I may ſay that Polychreſt has ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized it ſelf, and has often exceeded our Expectations. And therefore, though from the Ground-plot we have already laid, one may gueſs what courſe muſt be taken in thoſe kind of Diſeaſes, yet for the publick Good we ſhall inlarge a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle upon it.</p>
            <p>In caſe of a bilious Cholick (which is eaſily diſcerned by the Temper of the Perſon troubled therewith, by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes he is ſubject to, ſuch as burning Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Light-headedneſs, by a bitter Taſte in the Mouth, by a frequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:171007:15"/>to Vomiting, and by a yellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Complexion) let the whole Doze be put in a Quart of Spring-water, or thin Veal-broth, and let the Patient take it as hot as he can poſſibly, in the ſpace of an hour and a half or two hours. But, if the Pains continue, and the Belly don't grow looſe, let him take another Doze either immediately after the firſt Doze is drunk up, or elſe ſix or ſeven Hours after. And, during this Interval, let him take ſome good nouriſhing Broth.</p>
            <p>For a pituitous Cholick (which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable by the good Complexion of the Perſon which is troubled with it, by the frequent Waters that run out of his Noſe and Mouth; and by the Rhumatiſms he is often affected with) let the whole Doze be put only in a Quart of aroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Decoction, or (for want thereof) of plain Water, and let the Patient take it, in the ſpace of an Hour or an Hour and a half at the moſt, as hot as he can drink it. And, if that be not ſufficient, (as moſt times it is not) let him take ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doze, Glaſs upon Glaſs, if he can
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:171007:15"/>bear with it; or elſe an Interval may be allowed him, during which the Patient muſt take good nouriſhing Broth.</p>
            <p>As for a windy Cholick, common to pituitous and melancholy People, and eaſy to be diſcerned by the Obſtructions of the Liver, Spleen, and Hypocondria, and by the Winds thoſe Perſons make both upwards and downwards, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable ſtretching of the Ventricle, by the grumbling noiſe and ſwelling of the Abdomen, by the bringing up of Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhments and Remedies, by being bound, and by a cloſing up of the Anus where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Injection of Cliſters is often hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; for this kind of Cholick, I ſay, let the whole Doze be put into a Quart of aromatick Decoction, adding to it ſome Flowers of Camomil and Claver, and let the Patient take it hot, one Glaſs full every quarter of an hour, or every half hour. At the ſame time let there be ſome Fomentations of Rue, Camomil, and Claver, be apply'd to the Part. And, whereas this is the moſt malignant and obſtinate of all the Cholicks, two or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:171007:16"/>three Dozes will be requiſite, to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken quicker or ſloower according to the Strength of the Patient.</p>
            <p>This withall take along with you, that whatever Cholick it is, aſſoon as the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent Pains are allay'd, it is abſolutely neceſſary by emollient or wind-expelling Cliſters to carry off the Humours that are got into the Bowels, and to purge the Patient aſſoon as he ſhall be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to endure new Evacuations, leſt ſome leven ſhould remain, which might diſorder him again.</p>
            <p>For a ſimple Diarrhea, let the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent take half the Doze in a Quart of Decoction, either of Barley or Bran. But, if there be any thing of Bloud, let there be added to the Decoction ſome handfuls of red Roſes, and of grains of Wall-wort very ripe, to be infus'd or boyl'd therein. The Uſe of which muſt be continued for the ſpace of two or three Days, till the Humour be a little ſweetned. After which, the Patient muſt be purged with the whole Doſe, in a Quart of Water, or of the ſame Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:171007:16"/>
            <p>In caſe of a <hi>Cholerd Morbus,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Patient lies under a great miſery, firſt an attempt muſt be made to put a ſtop to his Vomiting by a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus of Treacle and Myrrh, with a grain or two of Laudanum. Aſſoon as he has got ſome reſt, and hath recover'd ſtrength by ſome Yolks of Eggs, let him take by little and little, and from time to time, a Doze of the Powder in a Quart of Decoction, or warm Water. His Vomiting being ſtop'd, and the Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler having ceaſed its fermentation, let him be purged with the whole Doze in a Quart of Water, to be taken in the ſpace of an hour. Which muſt be reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated as often as occaſion ſhall ſerve, that nothing may remain either in the Stomach or Bowels, that may in time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken the Diſtemper.</p>
            <p>For hyſterical Suffocations and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Vapours, let half the Doze be put in a Quart of cold Water, to be taken in the ſpace of two or three hours. But, if the Patient have loſt his Senſes, and be not in a condition to take it in that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:171007:17"/>manner, let ſome dry Powder be put into his Mouth, or let there be ſo much of it diſſolv'd in ſome Water as he can take, which he ſhall take by ſpoonfuls, till he comes to himſelf again. Then let him take the half Doze as aforeſaid, and the next day let him be ſure to purge himſelf with a whole Doze in a Quart of cold Water. And, foraſumuch as thoſe ſuffocating Fumes are only cauſed by Obſtructions and fuliginous Matters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the ſmall Veſſels, where they ferment from time to time, and make Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploſions as it were, it would not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to cleanſe the Conduits, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it ſeveral Days together as an open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Remedy. This were the way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their frequent returns, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the Evil which oftentimes is but palliated.</p>
            <p>In caſe the menſtrual Blood be ſtop't, which often breeds the Jaundice, and is the common cauſe of hyſterical Vapours, the Polychreſt ought to be uſed in the manner preſcribed for all Obſtructions in general. Only 'tis to be obſerved, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:171007:17"/>the Patient muſt purge her ſelf with it two or three days before the time her monthly flowers ſhould come, that it may operate the better, and help Nature the more effectually in this kind of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But, if this Evacuation be ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed long ſince, and that ſeveral Ways have been try'd to rectify it, the Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chreſt muſt be uſed with the ſame aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity, and as long as is uſual with Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Waters. I mean, that one half or a fourth part of the Doze be put in a Quart of River or Spring Water, and two or three Quarts of the ſame be drunk up every morning, for the ſpace of four or five Weeks.</p>
            <p>Now this Remedy has in this Caſe many Advantages over the mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. As, amongſt others, the Certainty of its Nature and Effects, which cannot be aſſerted of the Minerals which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnate the mineral Springs. For, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that thoſe Minerals are not always certainly known, there happen ſometimes conſiderable Changes from Year to Year, by the Mixture and Concourſe of new
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:171007:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Matters, whereby their Property is much altered. Moreover 'tis a certain Truth, that there is no danger of keeping long in the Stomach this great quantity of Water that is drunk; neither is it a ſmall Conveniency and Satisfaction for one, that he can take this mineral artificial Water at all Times, and in all Places, 'Tis doubtleſs a great Conveniency for ſuch Perſons as are confined to a Place, either by their Calling, or for want of competent Means to tranſport themſelves to the Waters.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Polychreſt</hi> of <hi>Meſſieurs Seignette</hi> is ſold by <hi>Monſieur Barbeau,</hi> in Pall-mall, at the Sign of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> Town. Every Doze is made up in a Paper, with a Swan printed upon it, and this Motto <hi>Cum Sole &amp; Sale omnia fiunt.</hi> The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is ſealed up with a Seal, having the Name of <hi>Seignette</hi> in it.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
